Association of Polish Priests of Connecticut records 1952-1991 CPAA 86-03
Connecticut Polish American Archives, Elihu Burritt Library, Central Connecticut State University
Association of Polish Priests of Connecticut Records
1952-1991
Association of Polish Priests of Connecticut(APPC)
CPAA 86-03
4 boxes (2 linear ft.)
Connecticut Polish American Archives, Elihu Burritt Library, Central Connecticut State University
Collection illustrates establishment and years of activities of the Association of Polish Priests of Connecticut (APPC). The association was initially established under Polish name Zjednoczenie Kaplanow Polskich in 1915. The main mission of the association was to establish religious association of clergy who shared common ethnic heritage. The association represented interest of Polish clergy within the hierarchy of the Catholic Church which was almost exclusively run by clergy of the Irish heritage. The APPC was instrumental in organizing celebration of the Millennium of Polish Christianity in 1966, which was a hallmark of public manifestation of religious and cultural links between Polish Americans and the country of their forefathers. The association made numerous financial contributions to the Catholic Church in Poland and sponsored major book publication - a biography of Monsignor Bojnowski. In February of 1991 the association became an affiliate member of a national organization - the Polish American Priests Association which was established in San Antonio, Texas.
Historical Note
Priests from Connecticut Polish catholic parishes in Connecticut formed Association of Polish Priests of Connecticut initially under the Polish name Zjednoczenie Polskich Kaplanow in 1915. For over thirty years Rev. John J. Pitrus led the association. In the 1960s the organization started evolving towards more formal structure and the first Constitution was approved in 1967. It listed its goals as promotion and effective communication among priests of Polish origin. It provided priests with ways to find solutions to common problems of ethnic parishes and Catholics of Polish origin. The association promoted religious, cultural and social development of parishioners of Polish origin. Priests of Polish origin were looking for ways to find support and solutions to the problems of ethnic parishes and yet the catholic hierarchy was not openly support ethnic parishes. The hierarchy within the catholic church was mostly Irish and priests were of non-Irish origin. It was not easy to get promoted and receive help from the church administration. Therefore the Association of Polish Priests in Connecticut was a medium to find common ground to problems and their solutions and also provided social network for ethnic priests. The celebration of the Millennium of Polish Christianity in 1966 was the first state wide manifestation of strong religious and cultural roots of Polish American catholics with Poland. Several years later, in 1969, the association celebrated the 50th anniversary of Poland's independence and during the same year they invited Cardianl Karol Wojtyla of Cracow to Connecticut, who later become Pope John Paul II. In 1991 the APPC celebrated the 150th anniversary of the oldest Polish parish in Connecticut, the Saint Stanislaus church in Meriden. The following years brought more anniversaries and reasons for celebration and displaying unity among Polish and Polish American clergy.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
Material in the collection partially illustrates the history and evolution of the association. The first bound volume of minutes, written in Polish, is dated from 1946 till 1971. Additional minutes are arranged by date together with correspondence; other documents related to major events and projects organized by the Association are also arranged by date. Material related to significant events like Poland's Millennium of Christianity is arranged separately. Collection also includes copy of a constitution, mailing lists, sermons, a typescript of publication related to the history of the association entitled "An Interpretive History" by Rev. T. Mierzwinski (1971, 45 pp.), and several photo albums from various events. Material is arranged in 3 series: Series I: Minutes and correspondence, Series II: Poland's Millennium of Christianity and other anniversaries, Series III: History, constitution and activities.
The collection is open for research.
The records were donated by Msgr. John P. Wodarski, who was a president of the organization at that time. First part was donated in 1986 and the second in 1991.
Search Terms
Association of Polish Priests of Connecticut.; Wodarski, John P.(John Paul), 1905-; Mierzwinski, Theophil T., 1924-; Catholics, Polish -- Connecticut.; Polish Americans -- Religious life -- Connecticut.; New Britain (Conn.: Town); Correspondence; Minutes; Clippings; Photographs; Financial records
Related Material
Rev. John P. Wodarski Collection, CPAA 86-02
Rev. Alphonse P. Fiedorczyk Papers, CPAA 88-06
- Series 1. Minutes and correspondence, 1946-1991
  - Minutes of Association of Polish Priests of Connecticut, Hartford Diocese., 1946-1971 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Minutes, 1957-1962 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Minutes, 1972-1979 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Minutes, 1979-1981 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Minutes, 1981-1983 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1952-1958 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1960-1965 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1967-1971 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1974-1979 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Minutes and scattered correspondence, 1980-1985 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, notes, memos, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, notes, memos, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, minutes and related photographs (from the Harvest Festival in New Britain), 1989 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, minutes, memos, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence and related material, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Meeting announcements, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Series 2. Poland's Millennium of Christianity and other anniversaries, 1966-1991
  - Correspondence, announcements, pt.1, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Millennium of Poland's Christianity - correspondence, announcements, pt.1, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Millennium of Poland's Christianity - correspondence, announcements, pt.2, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Millennium of Poland's Christianity - program, homily delivered during the mass and related notes, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Millennium of Poland's Christianity - financial contributions, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Millennium of Poland's Christianity - clippings, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Tribute to Mary celebration - correspondence, program, financial contributions, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Cardinal Karol Wojtyla visit - program, announcements, financial contributions, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Cardinal Karol Wojtyla's visit - clippings, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Celebration of the election of Cardinal Karol Wojtyla to be the Pope John Paul II - correspondence, announcements, program, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Celebration of the election of Cardinal Karol Wojtyla to be the Pope John Paul II - correspondence, announcements, program, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Century of Polonia Celebration - letterhead, logo, buttons, special prayer cards, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Century of Polonia Celebration 1891-1991 - Jozef Cardinal Glemp, Polish Primate, visit to Connecticut - correspondence, official program and other material related to the event (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Visit of Cardinal Gulbinowicz from Wroclaw, Poland - photo album, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Series 3. History, constitution and activities, 1967-1990
  - "The Association of Polish Priests in Connecticut: an interpretative history" by Rev. Theophil Mierzwinski, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - "Koscielne dzieje Polonii w Connecticut, 1870-1986 by Rev. Boleslaw Kumor, circa 1990 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Constitution, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Bojnowski book project - proposal, correspondence, 1969-1974 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - 3 letters concerning young priests of the association, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Deceased members of the association, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Association of Polish Priests - memorial mass, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Mailing list, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Financial records, 1941-1978 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Financial donations to assist Catholic Church in Poland and to scholarship fund at SS. Cyril & Methodius Seminary, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Financial donations for Catholic Relief in Poland, related correspondence, receipts, and photograph of Msgr. Wodarski, Rev. Wysocki and unnamed priest, 1980-1982 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Financial donations to Pope John Paul II Pilgrims' Center, between 1980-1985 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Copy of an acknowledgment of financial donation to Solidarity Trade Unions in Poland signed by Lech Walesa, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Vatican II changes in the Mass liturgy and its implementation by Association of Polish Priests of Connecticut, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Vicar for the Clergy, nomination of Msgr. John P. Wodarski, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - List of undergraduate and graduate students from the Holy Cross Parrish, 1969-1970 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Impressions of American Polonia, an essay by Bishop Albin Matysiak from Poland, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Cardianl Stefan Wyszynski justification for Beatification process of Father Maximilian Kolbe, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Report from the Ethnic Convention of clergy and non clergy delegates, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - St. Stanislaus church in Meriden vs. Loyal Parishioners Group controversy, related correspondence and clippings, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Sermon delivered by Msgr. L.B. Blecharczyk during mass for Katyn Massacre victims, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - The historical geography of Polish American Ecclesiastical Institutions, an essay by Daniel S. Buczek, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Memorial mass for APPC, photo album, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Msgr. George Bartlewski's 70 Anniversary of Priesthood Jubilee, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Program of the Polish American Priest Convention, San Antonio, Texas, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 25)